Guide to the Pauline Layton papers, 1967-1999
Layton, Pauline papers, 1967-1999
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Pauline Layton papers, 1967-1999
7620
Pauline Layton
0.5 cubic ft.
Manuscripts, clippings, pamphlets and other published materials, videos.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Documents from the creation and early years of Cornell's lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgendered student groups, and the Cornell Women's Studies Program (1968-1981). Pamphlets, articles, and other documents on the women's, sexual liberation, and gay liberation movements of the late 1960's and 1970's. Layton's reflections on her own gender and sexual identity. Videos concerning AIDS and equal rights for gays and lesbians.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Pauline Layton is a native Ithacan who studied mathematics at Cornell, but later became a musician, writer, and videographer.
Member of Cornell's Student Homophile League, 1968-1970; member of University of Massachusetts at Amherst Student Homophile League, 1970-1972; attended meetings of Cornell's GayPAC, 1979-1981.
Used local Public Access Television facilities to produce informative programming about AIDS-related services and also to campaign for local legislation in support of gay equal rights in housing and employment.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The collection contains documents from and reflections on the creation and early years of Cornell's lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgendered student groups and the Cornell Women's Studies Program (1968-1981), plus pamphlets, articles, bibliographies and other ephemeral publications expressing views of the women's, sexual liberation, and gay liberation movements of the late 1960's and 1970's. The collection also contains Layton's reflections on her own gender and sexual identity, including "A personal history in bi-gender mode," written 1998; pieces about transvestism and transsexualism written as she joined a bisexual support group in 1981; and an unsent letter to Janice Raymond, author of The Transsexual Empire.
Also, videos of programs produced by Layton and Ben Curtis for local cable television concerning the AIDS crisis in Tompkins County, and Local Law C, which passed in December 1991, and which included sexual orientation among the characteristics that could not be discriminated against in housing, credit, and employment. This show was produced to inform the public and allay fears about the law before a public hearing held in November.
A 1999 essay on teasing, gay-baiting, and violence among school children, including thoughts on the 1999 Columbine High School shooting in Littleton, Colorado.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Layton, Pauline.; Curtis, Ben.; Cornell University. Women's Studies Program.; Cornell University. Cornell Gay Liberation.; Cornell University. Student Homophile League.; Cornell University. Gay People at Cornell.; Cornell University--Students.; Cornell University--Societies, etc.; Cornell University. Gay People's Center.
Subjects:
AIDS (Disease)--Study and teaching.; Bisexuality.; Bullying.; Gay college students--Societies, etc.; Gays--Societies, etc.; Gender identity.; Hate crimes--United States.; Homophobia.; Homosexuality.; Lesbians--Societies, etc.; Transsexualism.; Transvestism.
Places:
Ithaca (N.Y.)--Politics and government.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Women's Studies Collections
Box 1
Series II. Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Collections
Box 1
Series III. Videos
Videos 377, 378
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Women's Studies Collections
  - Women's Studies at Cornell; text of Kate Millett speech at Cornell; NOW printed material, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cornell Chronicle "Report on Female Studies Conference", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Women's Periodicals: SDS Women's Liberation Resolution, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pauline Layton Women's Studies bibliography (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Magazine Articles, 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Magazine articles, 1969-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Articles by or about Cornell professors, 1970-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Women's liberation literature acquired at Cornell, printed by Glad Day Press, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Women's liberation literature acquired at U.Mass at Amherst, printed by New England Free Press, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The physiology of sex, 1967-1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II. Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, & Transgender Collections
  - History of the Student Homophile League (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Personal writings; correspondence: notes, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Clippings important to Student Homophile League history, 1966-1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Student Homophile League constitutions; SHL newsletters and handouts, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Student Homophile League table handouts; Society for Individual Rights Pocket Lawyer handed out by Dr. Frank Kameny, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Columbia SHL, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gay Flames pamphlets packet; U.Mass SHL, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - SHL or gay items; "Why People Didn't Like Jerry Moldenhauer"; personal writings (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gay magazine articles, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Gay comic strips, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Layton bibliography and notes from reading (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Androgyny: special issue of Women: A Journal of Liberation, and New York Times article, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Transvestism and transsexualism, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Transvestism and transsexualism, etc., 1980-1998 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "A personal history in a bi-gender mode", 1998 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Transvestism and transsexualism, personal aspects (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Personal writings on sexuality, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Boston Phoenix article on transsexualism, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Essay on teasing, gay-baiting, and violence among school children, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Series III. Videos
  Programs produced by Layton and Ben Curtis for local cable television concerning the AIDS crisis in Tompkins County, and Local Law C, which passed in December 1991.
  - Video, V-377
  - Video, V-377